Finding Aid for Michigan Historical Records Survey records, 1936-1942
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Historical Records Survey records 1936-1942
Michigan Historical Records Survey.
86745 Ca 2
Reports and administrative records of WPA project to survey historical records in Michigan; includes correspondence, drafts of guides to county archives, proceedings of county boards of supervisors, field reports of workers, and copies of land patents for some counties; also material relating to the history of Blacks in Michigan.
47 linear feet
68 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the Michigan Historical Records Survey (Donor Number 862 ) were received from the Works Progress Administration in 1942.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Historical Records Survey (H.R.S.) was sponsored by the Works Progress Administration (W.P.A.)(known as the Work Projects Administration as of July 1, 1939) from 1935 to 1942. The purpose of the survey was to make unpublished government records and important privately-owned historical materials accessible to government officials, historians, legal scholars, and the general public. It was the largest survey of public records ever conducted in the United States. Luther Evans, the organizer of the Historical Records Survey, stated to a subcommittee of the U.S. Senate Committee on Education and Labor, on March 1, 1938, that the Survey's aim was to "build up a second library system in the nation, by making unpublished materials as widely known and readily available...as printed materials now are." He envisioned the H.R.S. being an important part of a "historical renaissance" in the United States and said, "American life will indeed achieve more dignity and richness as we study our past in the only way that it can be studied, that is, in the archives and other materials which the Historical Records Survey makes adequately accessible to us for the first time."
These lofty goals notwithstanding, in actual fact the Historical Records Survey was a Depression-era project to give jobs to unemployed white-collar workers - teachers, historians, clericals, and others - and, again in the words of Luther Evans, to "rehabilitate them, strengthen their moral fiber, give them renewed hope for the future." The projects upon which these people labored are described herein, followed by a description of the records themselves.
Although the Historical Records Survey was terminated before all the work that had been envisioned could be completed, what had been accomplished was significant. The program of the H.R.S. was quite broad, encompassing Federal Projects and State Projects. Federal Projects, sponsored and supervised by the H.R.S. at the national level from Washington D.C., included the Survey of Federal Archives (located in the states), Survey of County Records, Survey of Church Records, Manuscripts Survey, American Imprints Survey, Inventory of State Records, Inventory of Municipal Records, American Portraits Survey, Civilian Organizations Survey, Historical Buildings Survey, Maps Survey, Microfilm Survey of Public Records, Naturalization Records Survey, Newspapers Survey, Paintings and Statuaries Survey, Photographs Survey, School Records Survey, Emergency Disposition of Records Survey, and Vital Statistics Survey. State Projects included indexes (of newspapers, deeds, etc.), calendars of manuscript collections, subject-related surveys (e.g., in Michigan, the Inventory of Negro Manuscripts), and transcriptions of government and church records, especially vital statistics and county board of supervisors' minutes.
The Historical Records Survey was organized by Luther Evans toward the end of 1935. He served as its national director for about four years, until he became the director of the Library of Congress's Legislative Services Division. In 1940 he was succeeded by Sargent Child, who had been a field supervisor since the project's beginning. In Michigan the Survey began in 1936, directed by Assistant State Supervisor Dr. Milo Quaife, secretary and editor of the Detroit Public Library's Burton Historical Collection, and by Associate Supervisor William Jabine. Dr. Quaife retired from the Survey at the end of 1936 and Mr. Jabine became state director until 1939, when he was succeeded by Stuart Portner, who stayed on until the Historical Records Survey came to its premature end in 1942.
After Federal Project No. 1, of which the H.R.S. was one unit, lost its federal funding in 1939, the Historical Records Survey functioned as a nationwide series of locally-sponsored projects. In Michigan it was sponsored by the State Administrative Board, although the Federal government shared expenses.
The largest H.R.S. project in Michigan was the Survey of County Records, part of the W.P.A.'s Division of Professional and Service Projects. Field workers inventoried the public records of the counties by locating, describing, and classifying them for future ease of accessibility. In addition they compiled histories of the counties and descriptions of the organization and function of government units. These were to be published, together with the inventories, as guides for each of the 83 counties in Michigan. Although work was done on each county, only a dozen guides were ever published. All of the H.R.S. publications and most of the unpublished materials are housed in the Michigan Historical Collections, located at the Bentley Historical Library. Some other unpublished materials are at the Burton Historical Collection at the Detroit Public Library (see a listing of their holdings in Appendix III of this finding aid).
The Manuscripts Survey was another important H.R.S. project. Margaret Sherburne was in charge on the national level and Dr. Bernhard Uhlendorf directed the Michigan survey. In 1940 the University of Michigan's Michigan Historical Collections became a cosponsor with the State Administrative Board for the statewide manuscripts survey and for the church records survey, both of whose publications are housed at the Bentley. A Guide to Manuscript Depositories in Michigan, published in 1940, was the first product of the Manuscripts Survey. The guide was produced under the auspices of the W.P.A.'s Division of Professional and Service Projects and included descriptions of the state's libraries, museums, and historical societies and their holdings. The inventory upon which the guide was based was a cooperative effort between Survey staff and the state's librarians and curators. Next came the Guide to Manuscript Collections in Michigan, prepared under the auspices of the W.P.A.'s Division of Community Service Programs (formerly the Division of Professional and Service Projects). Volume 1, an inventory of the Michigan Historical Collections, was issued in 1941 and Volume 2, an inventory of other University of Michigan collections, appeared in 1942. Calendars of two significant collections were published (filed under Historical Records Survey in the library's catalog of printed materials): Calendar of the Baptist Collection of Kalamazoo College, Kalamazoo, Michigan and Calendar of the John C. Dancy Correspondence, 1898-1910 (these are also held by the Library of Michigan and by the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints - see Appendices II and IV. They also have Vol. 1 of the Guide to Manuscript Collections in Michigan.). Many other private collections never got beyond the inventory stage, but these inventories are also in the H.R.S. collection at the Bentley.
A significant subject-related manuscript survey was the Inventory of Negro Manuscripts, the brainchild of Dr. Carter G. Woodson. The project was sometimes called the Negro Manuscripts Survey or, in Loretta Heffner's The WPA Historical Records Survey: A Guide to the Unpublished Inventories, Indexes, and Transcripts (Chicago: The Society of American Archivists, 1980), the Survey of Negro Historical Papers. In Michigan it was compiled by the Negro Manuscripts Unit of the Michigan H.R.S. as part of the W.P.A.'s Division of Community Service Programs. Under the direction of Dr. Bernhard Uhlendorf, director of the Manuscripts Survey, the project was organized by Christopher Alston in 1939 and run, after Mr. Alston moved on to other tasks, by historian Robert Hayden. The field workers (all Black) surveyed the Black community in the Detroit metropolitan area and the collections of the Burton Historical Collection at the Detroit Public Library. They searched for original records and papers, both of organizations and of individuals, which would shed light on the social and political history of Blacks in America. In 1941, the Survey published the Calendar of the John C. Dancey Correspondence, 1898-1910. Two other Survey products went unpublished: an essay on Black history in Michigan, attributed to Robert Hayden by Mr. Alston, and a calendar of correspondence discovered in the survey. Copies of the essay and calendar were bound into one volume entitled History of the Negro in Michigan, which is in the Bentley Historical Library, along with the published Dancey calendar and all the unpublished material. Other material relating to Black history can be found in some of the county files, especially Cass County.
The work of the American Imprints Survey was to document the history of American printing. It was compiled from a survey of thousands of libraries in the U.S., as well as some private collections and historical societies. The survey aimed to list, on a state-by-state basis, all old publications in the United States: books, pamphlets, and broadsides. "Old" meant anything from the beginning of printing through 1876, when copyrighting was introduced (later, for the western states). The Michigan Imprints Survey published Preliminary Check List of Michigan Imprints, 1796-1850 in 1942 under the auspices of the W.P.A.'s Division of Community Service Programs. It is arranged chronologically by year of publication and includes for each Michigan publication a listing of author, title, place of publication, pagination, and locations anywhere in the United States as of the time the survey was conducted. The information gathered was cleared through the National Union Catalog and revealed the existence of many publications which had previously been unknown. Bibliographer Douglas McMurtrie was the national director and Jacques Jean Engerrand was the state supervisor for Michigan. The Bentley Library has the published volume (listed in the printed materials catalog), as well as seven linear feet of notes on all the items discovered in the survey, from which the publication was compiled. These notes are listed in the manuscripts catalog under Michigan Imprints Inventory and cover publications of the years 1796-1876 (note the longer time span).
The Federal Writers Project commenced in 1935 and operated in many of the counties of the nation. According to a Michigan Writers Project blurb put out by the WPA, the purpose of the project was to "interpret the life, the history, and the local setting of the community to the state and to the nation." This project produced many publications: state and local guides, tour books, folklore and ethnic studies, children's books, and almanacs, many of which are in the Bentley Library. The Michigan Writers Project was transferred to the State WPA in 1939 and writer Harold Titus became state supervisor. The Historical Records Survey was under the Federal Writers Project for a year, so some of their records were interfiled. The Bentley has a few Michigan Writers Project records in the H.R.S. collection.
The purpose of the WPA Statewide Museums Project was to establish, organize, operate, and improve local museums throughout the state of Michigan, with all that entails. The main sponsor was the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan and cosponsors were the individual museums. Dorothy Myers was consultant and state supervisor of the Museums Project and Dr. Carl Guthe, director of museums at the university and a member of the project's advisory committee, was also very involved with it. Museums in Kalamazoo, Battle Creek, Holland, Grand Rapids, Lansing, East Lansing, Port Huron, Alpena, Ann Arbor, and Detroit were all greatly assisted by the program. Although the museums project was separate from the H.R.S., the records that came from the University of Michigan were interfiled with the Michigan H.R.S. material.
In 1942, when there was no longer a need to provide "make-work" projects because of the "real" work needed for the war effort, the Historical Records Survey was terminated. In Michigan, most of the records of the H.R.S. were given, shortly thereafter, to the Michigan Historical Collections, which was the official cosponsor of the project and the official depository for the H.R.S.'s unpublished materials as well as its publications. Other records were given to the Detroit Public Library's Burton Historical Collection (see Appendix III): 2 boxes of correspondence and reports; 4 boxes of typescript drafts on the following counties: Charlevoix, Chippewa, Clare, Dickinson, Genesee (which did get published), Gogebic, Houghton, Huron, Keweenaw, Lapeer, Macomb, Menominee, Midland, Missaukee, Oakland, St. Clair, and Tuscola; and 22 boxes of correspondence and field forms for the Inventory of Church and Synagogue Archives in Michigan, whose publications, as already mentioned, are housed in the Bentley Historical Library. The State Library of Michigan, in Lansing, has most of the Historical Records Survey's publications (see Appendix II). The State Archives, also in Lansing, has indexes to vital records and listings of WPA enterprises (complete with costs and much other information, very useful for any researcher studying the WPA). The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints has microfilm copies of many of the H.R.S.'s publications (see Appendix IV). Loretta Hefner compiled The W.P.A. Historical Records Survey: A Guide to the Unpublished Inventories, Indexes, and Transcripts (published by the Society of American Archivists in 1980), which contains additional locations of H.R.S. materials throughout the nation. In addition, the National Archives in Washington D.C. contains a great deal of H.R.S. material, in Record Group 69 (see Appendix V). There is a related collection at the Bentley Library. Since the Michigan Historical Collections was official cosponsor and some of the WPA work was done in it s offices (as well as having some of its own work done by WPA workers), the Bentley Library also has WPA files in the "University of Michigan. Michigan Historical Collections." archival collection. These consist of correspondence, mostly, in connection with the Michigan Writers Project, the Historical Records Survey, and the Statewide Museums Project.
Due to its poor quality, much of the paper used in the Historical Records Survey has deteriorated badly over the years. In order to preserve the information contained therein, most of the collection has been microfilmed. Some materials have been preserved in their original form without being filmed and some have been retained after filming, but most of the papers that were filmed have been discarded. This is described in more detail in the following description of the records.
The Historical Records Survey record group documents the activities and the product of the legions of depression era workers who inventoried the records held in county courthouses, municipal offices some private repositories. The records include correspondence, drafts of guides to county archives, proceedings of county boards of supervisors, field reports of workers, and copies of land patents for some counties; also material relating to the history of Blacks in Michigan.
Originally the H.R.S. records transferred to the Michigan Historical Collections measured about 121 linear feet. After processing, the collection consisted of 26 feet of records relating to the H.R.S. and 65 feet of transcripts of county and municipal records. Of the remaining 30 feet, 29.5 feet of duplicate, extraneous, or insignificant materials were discarded (described in more detail further on) and approximately half of a linear foot of printed material was transferred to the library's printed collection.
The H.R.S. material has been divided into the following series:
Survey of County Records
Survey of Municipal Records
Survey of Federal Records
Survey of State Records
WPA Project Files
Manuscripts Survey
Inventory of Negro Manuscripts
Transcripts of County Records
Transcripts of Municipal Records
Photographs
Historical Records Survey Correspondence
Survey Forms of 1987 Survey of Records in Counties and Municipalities.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Alcona County (Mich.); Alger County (Mich.); Allegan County (Mich.); Alpena (Mich.); Alpena County (Mich.); Antrim County (Mich.); Architecture.; Archival surveys.; Arenac County (Mich.); Baraga County (Mich.); Barry County (Mich.); Battle Creek (Mich.); Bay City (Mich.); Bay County (Mich.); Benzie County (Mich.); Berrien County (Mich.); Branch County (Mich.); Calhoun County (Mich.); Cass County (Mich.); Charlevoix County (Mich.); Charlotte (Mich.); Cheboygan (Mich.); Cheboygan County (Mich.); Chippewa County (Mich.); Civilian Conservation Corps (U.S.); Clare County (Mich.); Clinton County (Mich.); County government--Records and correspondence.; Crawford County (Mich.); Delta County (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.). Recorder's Court.; Dickinson County (Mich.); Eaton County (Mich.); Emmet County (Mich.); Escanaba (Mich.); Flint (Mich.); Genesee County (Mich.); Gladwin County (Mich.); Gogebic County (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Grand Traverse County (Mich.); Gratiot County (Mich.); Hamtramck (Mich.); Hillsdale County (Mich.); Houghton County (Mich.); Huron County (Mich.); Ingham County (Mich.); Ionia County (Mich.); Iosco County (Mich.); Iron County (Mich.); Isabella County (Mich.); Jackson (Mich.); Jackson County (Mich.); Kalamazoo (Mich.); Kalamazoo County (Mich.); Kalkaska County (Mich.); Kent County (Mich.); Keweenaw County (Mich.); Lake City (Mich.); Lake County (Mich.); Lapeer County (Mich.); Leelanau County (Mich.); Lenawee County (Mich.); Livingston County (Mich.); Luce County (Mich.); Mackinac County (Mich.); Macomb County (Mich.); Manistee County (Mich.); Marquette (Mich.); Marquette County (Mich.); Mason County (Mich.); Mecosta County (Mich.); Menominee (Mich.); Menominee County (Mich.); Michigan. Dept. of Conservation.; Michigan Historical Records Survey.; Michigan. Liquor Control Commission.; Michigan. Office of the Auditor General.; Michigan. State Board of Health.; Michigan State Library.; Michigan State Police.; Midland County (Mich.); Missaukee County (Mich.); Monroe County (Mich.); Montcalm County (Mich.); Montmorency County (Mich.); Muskegon (Mich.); Muskegon County (Mich.); Newaygo County (Mich.); Niles (Mich.); Oakland County (Mich.); Oceana County (Mich.); Ogemaw County (Mich.); Ontonagon County (Mich.); Osceola County (Mich.); Oscoda County (Mich.); Otsego County (Mich.); Ottawa County (Mich.); Petoskey (Mich.); Port Huron (Mich.); Presque Isle County (Mich.); Public records.; Roscommon County (Mich.); Saginaw County (Mich.); Saint Clair County (Mich.); Saint Joseph County (Mich.); Sanilac County (Mich.); Schoolcraft County (Mich.); Shiawassee County (Mich.); Tuscola County (Mich.); United States. Dept. of Agriculture.; United States. Dept. of Commerce.; United States. Dept. of Justice.; United States. Dept. of Labor.; United States. Farm Credit Administration. Production Credit Division.; United States. Navy Dept.; United States. Resettlement Administration.; United States. War Dept.; United States. Work Projects Administration.; Van Buren County (Mich.); Washtenaw County (Mich.); Wayne County (Mich.); Wexford County (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Courthouses--Michigan.; Exhibitions.; Galleries and museums.; Guthe, Carl E. (Carl Eugen), 1893-1974; Photographs.; United States. Work Projects Administration.
- Survey of County Records
  The Survey of County records series, comprising 15 linear feet of material, is arranged alphabetically by county. record types inventoried for each county may include some or all of the following: Correspondence; Historical Material; Historical Material - Government Organization; Inventory of Government Department Holdings; Housing, Care, and Accessibility of Records (which deals with storage and arrangement); Maps (of the counties); and Inventory of Maps in the Counties. The records reflect the fact that the field workers fully researched some counties while paying scant attention to others.
  Correspondence between field workers in the counties and their supervisors in district offices or the state H.R.S. office contains descriptive and historical information about the counties as well as information concerning the workings of the H.R.S. project. In some areas the work went along quite smoothly, but in others the field workers faced numerous difficulties: getting permission to examine government records and to have a place to work, facing officials whose attitude ranged from indifference to outright hostility; attempting to inventory records which were poorly organized and stored in inaccessible places; and even obtaining adequate training and basic office supplies from the WPA Charles Johnson, a field worker in Ionia County, wrote articulately on the workings of the project and his letters make good reading (see roll 13). Three counties - Alger, Ingham, and Marquette - had H.R.S. district supervisors' offices, so their correspondence files contain information about whole regions as well as good descriptions of the project (letters which mentioned only one county have been transferred to that county's files). H.R.S. correspondence is also a source of information about county records. Sometimes it reveals what had happened to records which no longer existed when the survey was conducted and sometimes it is a source of inventory information - in the case of Ingham County the only source, since both the forms and the completed inventory (if there ever was one) are lost. Within each county, correspondence is arranged chronologically and anything of a routine or insignificant nature has been discarded. General instructions, issued to each field worker in the state, have not been retained for each county but only where they were first found in processing and so would tend to be concentrated at the beginning of the alphabetical listing of counties. Any researcher studying the H.R.S. project would want to consult all of the correspondence; therefore, in addition to each county's correspondence being microfilmed with its other material, all the correspondence has been preserved after filming and grouped together, arranged alphabetically by county.
  Historical information is divided into two broad categories: Historical Material for general information and Historical Material - Government Organization (what the H.R.S. called "legal research") for that relating to the government departments. For both, like information has been gathered together and arranged, for the most part, according to the organizational scheme in the H.R.S. published guides.